<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>History</title>
    <author email="hohwille@users.sourceforge.net">J&#246;rg Hohwiller</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Project History">
      <subsection name="2000-??-??">
        <p>
        <a href="team-list.html#Contributors">Christoph Bauer</a> 
        created a tcl/tk script called 
        <a href="http://www.rhrk.uni-kl.de/~bauerc">mp3man</a>.
        His idea was to create a program that organinzes mp3 files. 
        It plays them using and external player program (mpg123).
        MySQL is used by mp3man to store information about each song like
        title, artist, genre, ranking, backup-media-id, etc.
        Now during playing the user can influence the ranking with the buttons
        "I like this song" or "I hate this song". The program also archieves
        the mp3-files to a backup-media (CD), associates each backup-media
        with a unique ID that the user should write on the media. Now the
        program can delete songs with bad ranking if disk space is low. If
        a deleted song is choosen by the user to be played (the entry is
        still in the db), the program tells the ID of the backup-media to
        insert and restores the song to the hard-disk. Finally the program
        can import audio-CDs and automatically fill the database (using CDDB).
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2001-01-30">
        <p>
        <a href="team-list.html#Contributors">Christoph Bauer</a> and
        <a href="team-list.html#Developers">J&#246;rg Hohwiller</a> (me)
        decided to start a project called pythonDJ, that was registered at
        <a href="http://www.sourceforge.net">sourceforge</a>.
        The name already tells that the implementation was done in python.
        The project should be like mp3man, but more fexible and also os-independent 
        using wxPython.<br/>
        Actually this project died before any useful code was done:
        We had different ideas of the project and especially I
        decided not to write a big team project in a non typed script language.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2001-04-11">
        <p>
        I (<a href="team-list.html#Developers">J&#246;rg Hohwiller</a>) founded the 
        project myDJ which was the replacement for pythonDJ, but written in Java.
        <a href="team-list.html#Contributors">Christoph Bauer</a> did not like 
        to join the project, because he did not like my decision to write the 
        program in Java.<br/>
        <a href="mailto:carlos_santos@users.sourceforge.net">Carlos Santos</a> 
        joined the team as webmaster and created the www-sites. I wrote some 
        code for this project that was only available in the CVS.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2001-10-01">
        <p>
        I (<a href="team-list.html#Developers">J&#246;rg Hohwiller</a>) founded this 
        project (m-m-m) as a replacement for myDJ. The reason was that I thought
        that all the concepts and ideas of myDJ were so generic that 
        they can be used not only for music but for any kind of data.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2001-11-14">
        <p>
        The project m-m-m was registered at 
        <a href="http://www.sourceforge.net">sourceforge</a>.
        Some code was devloped and available via CVS (module core) but because 
        spare time was rare the project was sleeping for a very long while.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2004-01-01">
        <p>
        After years I finally decided to work active on the project again. 
        A lot of refactoring was done dividing the project into separate components (COP).
        Avalon was choosen as framework for COP driven design. 
        Maven was evaluated and finally chosen as project management tool.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2004-07-01">
        <p>
         Because my plans for the project make it impossible to have a working release 
         before 2006, I decided to change the codebase to JDK 5.0 (named JDK 1.5 at this time).
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2004-07-16">
        <p>
        Changed License from GPL to LGPL.
        This step could be easily taken because no other author than me
        had produced any file or line of code for the project.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2004-2005">
        <p>
        Since there is no community and might not be before a first useable release,
        I decided to develop on my local subversion server until sourceforge will
        offer subversion as alternative to cvs. Please send me an email if you
        want to have the latest sources or would like to have the subversion repository
        visible to the public.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2005-06-24">
        <p>
        Switched from maven to maven2.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2005-08-01">
        <p>
        Changed License from LGPL to Apache Software Licenes for final freedom.
        This step could be easily taken because no other author than me
        had produced any file or line of code for the project.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2005-10-25">
        <p>
        Registered and set up subversion repository at projxpert.com. The projxpert team
        granted public read access for the subversion and gave a free upgrade because the
        project is open-source. Big thanks to projxpert.com.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2006-07-23">
        Deployed the maven2 site after the old site was not updated for over one year. From now on the site gets updated automatically by my server.
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="2006-08-28">
        Moved the subversion repository from projxpert.com to googlecode.com. The service at projxpert was good
        and the hosting maby even a little faster. Anyways for an open-source project it is easier for others
        to contribute since a google account is more common than one for projxpert. 
        Additionally the googlecode hosting service is intended for open-source projects.
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
