<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Multi Media Manager</title>
    <author email="hohwille@users.sourceforge.net">J&#246;rg Hohwiller</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Introduction">
      Welcome to the wonderful world of MMM. The initial goal of this project was to build a Multi-Media-Manager (MMM).
      However, in order to build this we first wanted to build a generic application framework for Java to build ontop.
      This is where we currently seem to end so please do not get confused by the project name and have a closer look.
      We could also rename this to <em>Modern-Mature-Modules</em>.
      To get started have a look at the <a href="images/Architecture.svg">technical architecture</a>.
      Please also read our strategic posting <a href="https://github.com/m-m-m/mmm/wiki/Rescue-the-java-world">Rescue the (Java) world</a>.
      <subsection name="Ready to use">
        This project provides the following generic components that can already be used now:
        <ul>
          <li><a href="mmm-persistence/index.html">mmm-persistence</a> provides code and best practices to build your persistence layer with JPA easier.</li>
          <li><a href="mmm-search/index.html">mmm-search</a> provides a full-text solution base on lucene.</li>
          <li><a href="mmm-util/index.html">mmm-util</a> contains powerful utilities.</li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    <section name="About MMM">
      MMM is a generic application framework that massively speeds up development of (complex) applications.
      It is based on common standards such as <em>Context and Dependency Injection</em> (CDI) by default using
      <a href="www.springframework.org">spring</a> or <em>Java Persistence Api</em> (JPA) by default using
      <a href="http://hibernate.org/">hibernate</a>. Most of such frameworks aim to be minimal invasive what
      is nice in general. However, development of large applications with only such frameworks is still not 
      efficient as you always have to implement a lot of general code in every project reinventing the wheel.
      Further there are hundreds of possible ways to do something and you can easily get on the wrong track.
      This project helps you to make the right decisions leading to a mature, flexible and powerful architecture
      that has proven success in various open-source and commercial medium to large scale projects.
      By providing a lot of reusable and generic code for all the common problems on your way this projects
      extremely speeds you up.
      <subsection name="Mission Statement">
        <ul>
          <li>Designed with beauty.</li>
          <li>Coded with passion.</li>
          <li>Tested with care.</li>
          <li>Documented with devotion.</li>
        </ul>      
        MMM is entirely written in Java. It makes extensive use of the Java 5 syntax.
        All code is written with focus on design &amp; quality and comes with detailed API documentation.<br/>
        The application is heavily based on the idioms separation of concerns (SoC) and inversion of control (IoC) 
        and therefore split into tiny components (see <a href="modules.html">modules</a>). This open architecture allows any 
        component implementation to be reused (by other projects) or be replaced (for custom needs).<br/>
        <b>ATTENTION:</b><br/>
        This mission statement applies to subprojects (modules) that are released. Modules that are NOT 
        released (version less than <code>1.0.0</code> including <code>1.0.0-SNAPSHOT</code>) may be 
        completely refactored, change their API or even dissappear completely.
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Project State">
        Even though the project exists for many years now, there is no multi-media-manager available.
        However, the application framework provided here has matured over the last years and many modules
        are going to be released officially within 2013.
        If you are looking for open, flexible and well-designed software components (see "Ready to use") 
        or you want to get involved (see <a href="https://github.com/m-m-m/mmm/wiki/Get-Involved">Get Involved</a>) 
        and let the vision of MMM become reality then you are at the right place.
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
