<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Multi Media Manager</title>
    <author email="hohwille@users.sourceforge.net">J&#246;rg Hohwiller</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Introduction">
      Welcome to the Project Multi-Media-Manager (MMM). The project is still 
      under development. Before you get lost, first some words of what you can 
      already find here.
      <subsection name="Ready to use">
        This project provides the following generic components that can already be used now:
        <ul>
          <li><a href="mmm-search/index.html">mmm-search</a> provides a full-text solution base on lucene.</li>
          <li><a href="mmm-util/index.html">mmm-util</a> contains powerful utilities.</li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    <section name="About MMM">
      The Multi-Media-Manager (MMM) is a generic application plattform and 
      a enterprise content management system (ECMS) with custom modules for 
      multi-media management build on top.
      <subsection name="Mission Statement">
        <ul>
          <li>Designed with beauty.</li>
          <li>Coded with passion.</li>
          <li>Tested with care.</li>
          <li>Documented with devotion.</li>
        </ul>      
        MMM is entirely written in Java. It makes extensive use of the Java 5 syntax.
        All code is written with focus on design &amp; quality and comes with detailed API
        documentation.<br/>
        The application is heavily based on the idioms separation of concerns (SoC) and
        inversion of control (IoC) and therefore split into tiny components 
        (see <a href="modules.html">modules</a>). This open architecture allows any 
        component implementation to be reused (by other projects) or be replaced (for custom needs).<br/>
        <b>ATTENTION:</b><br/>
        This mission statement applies to subprojects (modules) that are released. Modules that are NOT 
        released (version less than <code>1.0.0</code> including <code>1.0.0-SNAPSHOT</code>) may be 
        completely refactored, change their API or even dissappear completely.
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Project State">
        Even though the project exists for many years now, there is no CMS and no multi-media
        management available. If you are looking for open, flexible and well-designed software
        components (see "Ready to use") or you want to get involved (see 
        <a href="https://github.com/hohwille/mmm/wiki/Get-Involved">Get Involved</a>) and let the vision of 
        MMM become reality then you are at the right place.
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
