<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Native Language Support</title>
    <author email="hohwille@users.sourceforge.net">J&#246;rg Hohwiller</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="About MMM::NLS">
      <p>
      Applications that should be used by people all over the world need 
      <em>native language support</em> (NLS). The developers task is the
      <em>internationalization</em> (i18n) where the application has to 
      be written in a way that the code is (mostly) independent from 
      locale-specific informations. This at least means that all messages 
      that may be displayed to the end-user have to be accessed in a way 
      that allows <em>localization</em> (l10n) to the users locale.
      </p>
      <subsection name="The Problem">
        <p><img src="images/no-msg-dialog.png"/></p>
      	<p>
        Java already comes with great i18n support. But IMHO there are some
      	tiny peaces missing to complete the great puzzle of NLS:<br/>
        There is almost no support if an application needs NLS support 
      	that is handling multiple users with different locales concurrently 
      	(e.g. a web-application).<br/>
      	You will typically store your messages in a <code>ResourceBundle</code>.
        Now if you store the technical key of the bundle in a message or exception 
        the receiver needs the proper <code>ResourceBundle</code> to decode it
      	or he ends up with a cryptical message he can NOT understand (e.g. as 
      	illustrated by the screenshot).<br/>
      	On the other hand you need to know the locale of the receiver to do the 
      	l10n when creating the message or exception with the proper text.
        This is impossible to solve in may situations or leading to sick design.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="The Solution">
        <p>
        The solution is quite simple because again Java brings parts of the
        solution with <code>MessageFormat</code>:<br/>
        We simply bundle the message in default language together with 
      	the separated locale independent arguments in one container object 
      	that is called <code>NlsMessage</code>. Here is an example to clarify
      	the idea: The i18n message is "Hi {0}! How are you?" and the language
      	independent argument is the users name e.g. "Lilli". Now if we store 
      	these informations together we have all we need. To get the localized 
      	message we simply translate the i18n message to the proper language
      	and then fill in the arguments. If we can NOT translate we always have
      	the message in default language which is "Hi Lilli! How are you?".<br/>
      	But how do we translate the i18n message without artificial intelligence?
      	The answer is very easy: We simply use the bundle in default language 
      	and do a reverse lookup to get the technical key. Then we can lookup 
      	the proper message in the according bundle to translate it to the 
      	according locale.<br/>
      	All you have to do is creating a subclass of 
      	<code>AbstractResourceBundle</code> that declares public string contants
      	<source>
public class MyResourceBundle extends AbstractRespourceBundle {
  public static final String MSG_SAY_HI = "Hi {0}! How are you?";
  public static final String ERR_LOGIN_IN_USE = "Sorry. The login \"{0}\" is " +
    "already in use. Please choose a different login.";
}
      	</source>
        From your code you need to create the <code>NlsMessage</code> using this
      	constants:
      	<source>
String usersName = "Lilli";
NlsMessage msg = new NlsMessageImpl(MyResourceBundle.MSG_SAY_HI, usersName);
      	</source>
      	For exceptions there is additional support via 
      	<code>NlsException</code> and <code>NlsRuntimeException</code>.
        Simply derive your declared exceptions from one of these classes:
      	<source>
public class IllegalLoginException extends NlsException {
  public IllegalLoginException(String usedLogin) {
    super(MyResourceBundle.ERR_LOGIN_IN_USE, usedLogin);
  }
}
      	</source>
        Now if you throw a <code>IllegalLoginException</code>, it will behave as a
      	"regular" exception with an English message. Additionally it has methods
      	<code>getLocalizedMessage</code> and <code>printStackTrace</code> that
      	take a <code>NlsTranslator</code> interface as argument.
      	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
